George S. Snyderman Papers 1758-1995 1945-1985 Mss.Ms.Coll.51
American Philosophical Society
George S. Snyderman Papers
Bulk, 1945-1985
1758-1995
Mss.Ms.Coll.51
American Philosophical Society
3.0 Linear feet
Trained as an anthropologist under Frank Speck at the University of Pennsylvania, the ethnohistorian George Snyderman (1908- ) spent his career studying Seneca Indian religion, history, and culture. Snyderman edited the previously unpublished diaries of Halliday Jackson and John Phillips, Quaker missionaries to the Senecas in the late 18th and early 19th century. The Snyderman Papers includes a small volume of correspondence, along with manuscripts of works by Snyderman and colleagues, and copies of primary source materials pertaining to Seneca history. Of particular interest is his correspondence with anthropologists William N. Fenton, Merle Deardorff, and Frank Speck and with his Seneca consultant Clara Redeye and her daughter, Helen Harris, and photographs of the Allegany Senecas taken by Fenton and Speck.
Snyderman, George Simon, 1908-
Bibliography
Snyderman, George S., "Concepts of land ownership among the Iroquois and their neighbors" Bulletin of the Bureau of American Ethnology 149 (1951), 13-34. Call no.: 970.1 Pam. no.149
Snyderman, George S., "The manuscript collections of the Philadelphia Yearly Meeting of Friends pertaining to the American Indian" Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society 102 (1958), 613-620. Call no.: 506.73 Am4p
Snyderman, George S., "The function of wampum in Iroquois religion" Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society 105 (1961), 571-608. Call no.: 506.73 Am4p
Snyderman, George S., "Witches, witchcraft, and Allegany Seneca medicine," Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society 127 (1983), 263-277. Call no.: 506.73 Am4p
African American History Note
This collection contains at least one item which may be of interest to students of African American history:
Frobenius, Leo. "Early African Culture as an Indication of Present Negro Potentialities." n.d. 9 pages.
The cultures of the people of Africa vary greatly across the African continent. The paper examines the differences and commonalities of various historical African cultures and their effect on the "potentialities of present-day Negroes in Africa and America."
Related Archival Materials note
The Snyderman Papers are one of several collections at the APS that pertain to the ethnography and history of Seneca Indians, including the Papers of William N. Fenton, Elisabeth Tooker, Frank Speck, Anthony F. C. Wallace, and Paul A. W. Wallace.
Quaker missions to the Seneca Indians during the late 18th and early 19th centuries are documented in the Anthony F. C. Wallace Papers and in a ten reel microfilm set of the records of the Philadelphia Yearly Meeting Indian Committee (Film 824). The originals of the latter are housed in the Quaker Collection at Haverford College. Additional materials, including the originals of the journals found in the Snyderman Papers, are located at Haverford and at the Friends Historical Library at Swarthmore College.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Snyderman Papers have been donated by George S. Snyderman from 1987 to 1995. It is expected that further additions will be made to this collection.
Scope and Contents note
The George S. Snyderman Papers (1758-1995) contain correspondence, subject files, works by Snyderman and others, and photographs. The collection consists primarily of Snyderman's research notes and manuscripts about Seneca religion, medicine, and social organization. The most recent items in the collection are letters dated 1995.
The papers (7 boxes; 3.5 linear feet) are divided into five series:
Series I. Correspondence, 1940-1990 (2 boxes; 1 linear foot)
Series II. Subject files, 1758-1994 (0.5 boxes; 0.25 linear foot)
Series III. Works by Snyderman, 1939-ca.1985 (1.5 boxes; 0.75 linear foot)
Series IV. Works by others, 1758-1984 (1 box; 0. 5 linear foot)
Series V. Photographs, 1790-1993 (1 box; 0.5 linear foot)
Series I-III. Oversized material (1 box; 0.25 linear foot)
Oversized materials follow the same series arrangement as noted above. Cross-referencing to oversized material appears on the folders in the standard sized boxes. All photographs have been removed from Series I-IV and placed in Series V. Cross-references appear in the original series. Reprints have been moved to the printed materials collection of the APS Library. If a reprint was found as an enclosure, a photocopy of the title page was filed in its place. To retrieve reprints, consult the card catalog for printed materials. Audio-cassette recordings, three of Seneca music and one of Clara Redeye, have also been removed from the collection; to retrieve those items, consult the card catalog for manuscript materials.
Biographical/Historical note
George S. Snyderman was born in Philadelphia on August 23, 1908. After attending Temple University for his B.S. in Education (1931), he studied anthropology at the University of Pennsylvania under Frank G. Speck, receiving his M.A. in 1933 and his Ph.D. in 1948. His research centered on Seneca folklore, medicine, and social organization.
Snyderman worked at the Pennsylvania State Employment Service in Philadelphia from 1938 to 1961, occasionally conducting research about Native Americans west of the Ohio River for court cases involving Native American land claims being litigated by lawyer Felix S. Cohen. In 1961, Snyderman became Associate Director of the Jewish Employment and Vocational Service. He began lecturing at Temple University in 1963.
Snyderman is a member of the American Association for the Advancement of Science and the American Anthropological Association. He participated in the White House Conference on Children and Youth. He currently resides in Orchard Park, New York.
Akwesasne Counselor Organization.; Deardorff, Merle H., d.1971; Ettawageshik, Fred, 1896-1969; Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005; Frobenius, Leo; Harris, Helen; Parrish, John; Phillips, John; Pierce, John; Post, Frederick; Redeye, Clara; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950; Tantaquidgeon, Gladys; Witthoft, John; Africa; Allegany Reservation (N.Y.); Anthropology, ethnography, fieldwork; Cayuga Indians; Culture, community, organizations; Eastern Woodlands Indians; Ethnohistory; Gelatin silver prints; Indians of North America--New York (State); Iowa--Maps; Iroquois dance; Iroquois Indians--Dwellings; Maps.; Missouri--Maps; Mohawk Indians--Social life and customs; Ohio--Maps; Oneida Indians--Wisconsin; Photographic prints--Color; Photographs; Postcards; Seneca Indians--Missions; Seneca Indians--New York (State); Seneca Indians--Religion; Seneca Indians--Social life and customs; Seneca masks; Society of Friends--Missions
- Series I. Correspondence, 1940-1990, 2 boxes; 1 linear foot
  Scope and Contents note
  Incoming with comparatively little outgoing correspondence. The largest series in the collection, Series I is arranged alphabetically by correspondent's name and then chronologically within each folder. Unidentified correspondence has been filed as "Unidentified" and is arranged chronologically. Enclosed manuscripts have been removed from this series and placed in Series III or IV as appropriate. As with the reprints, a photocopy of the title page was filed with the original letter.
  Correspondents include anthropologists, government officials, students, Native Americans, and interested amateur anthropologists. Among the topics covered in this series are Iroquois ceremonies and customs and the business of the Pennsylvania State Employment Service. There are many letters from Clara Redeye, whom Snyderman met while doing fieldwork, and who, with her husband Sherman, adopted Snyderman in a Seneca ceremony in 1947. Also included are letters from Clara Redeye's daughter, Helen Harris. Both womens' letters detail daily life, social customs, and folklore of the Seneca of Allegany Reservation. Correspondence with Merle H. Deardorff and William N. Fenton documents the exchange of information on the Iroquois; Deardorff's correspondence also includes information about the construction of Kinzua Dam. Letters from Marcus Solomon Goldstein discuss various topics, including anthropology and life in Israel.
  - Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia. Library, 1952 (Box 1)
  - American Anthropological Association, 1953-1954,1991 (Box 1)
    Johnson, Frederick
  - American Anthropologist, 1958 (Box 1)
  - American Philosophical Society, 1950-1991 (Box 1)
  - Bowen, Merrill W. (Box 1)
    -See Ser.I, Cornplanter Indian Landowners Corporation
  - Broughton, John G. (Box 1)
    -See Ser.I, New York State Museum and Science Service
  - Bryn Mawr College, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Buffalo and Erie County Historical Society, 1980-1981 (Box 1)
    -See also Ser.I, Deardorff, Merle H.
  - Buffalo Philharmonic Orchestra Society, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Canada. Indian Affairs Branch, 1953,[1955] (Box 1)
  - Chester County Historical Society, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Cohen, Felix S., 1950 (Box 1)
  - Congdon, Charles E., 1951 (Box 1)
  - Cooper, John M., 1946 (Box 1)
  - Cornplanter Indian Landowners Corp., 1965 (Box 1)
    Bowen, Merrill W.
    United States. Army Engineer District, Pittsburgh
  - Crouse, Myrtle (Mrs. Clifford), 1947-1972 (Box 1)
    -See also Deardorff, Merle H., Aug. 1953
  - Cullen, William B. (Box 1)
    -See Ser.I, Hoffmann, Wilfred E.
  - Curry, Ed, 1972-1974,n.d. (Box 1)
  - Deardorff, Mary T. (Mrs. Merle H.), 1971-1972 (Box 1)
    Deardorff, Merle H.
  - Deardorff, Merle H. (Box 1)
    Buffalo Historical Society
    Kent, Don
    Taplinger, Dick
    Voget, Fred W.
    Wallace, Anthony F.C.
    -See also Ser.I, Deardorff, Mary
    -See also Ser.I, Fenton, William
    -See also Ser.I, Snow, Kenneth (Mrs.)
    -See also Ser.I, Snow, Lena
    -See also Ser.I, White, Clayton
    - Folder #1, 1943-1947 (Box 1)
    - Folder #2, 1948-1953 (Box 1)
    - Folder #3, 1954-1970,n.d. (Box 1)
  - Depp, Frederick C., 1972 (Box 1)
  - Devereux Foundation, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Dilworth, Richardson, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Dodge, Ernest Stanley, 1949,1951 (Box 1)
  - Dowler, Maxine, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Einhorn, Art[hur], 1973 (Box 1)
  - Encyclopedia Americana, 1955 (Box 1)
  - English, Nicholas Conover, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Eshelman, John E., 1953 (Box 1)
  - Fadden, Ray, n.d. (Box 1)
    Native American images note: charts of illustrations by Ray Fadden from the Akwesasne Mohawk Counselor organization, St. Regis Mohawk reservation, Hogansbury, New York. Images include utensils, musical instruments, clothes, and masks. -See Oversized
  - Fenton, William Nelson, 1940-1994 (Box 1)
    Deardorff, Merle H. (1940)
    Nichols, Robert Hastings (1951)
  - Francello, Joseph A., 1980-1981 (Box 1)
  - General, Alex (Deskaheh), 1949 (Box 1)
    -See also Ser.I, Speck, Frank G.
  - Gibson, Edmond P., 1950 (Box 1)
  - Goldstein, Marcus Solomon, 1986-1994,n.d. (Box 1)
  - Grace, Natalie, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Hallowell, A[lfred] I[rving], 1954 (Box 1)
  - Harris, Helen (Box 1)
    - Folder #1, 1948-1986 (Box 1)
    - Folder #2, 1987-1991 (Box 2)
    - Folder #3, 1992-1995,n.d. (Box 2)
  - Harris, Linda, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Harris, Rosalie, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Hartwick College, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Haverford College. Library. The Quaker Collection, 1952,1983 (Box 2)
    -See also Ser.II, Haverford College Library
  - Hay, John, 1959-1960 (Box 2)
  - Herzfeld, Regina F., 1969 (Box 2)
  - Hoffmann, Wilfred E., 1946 (Box 2)
    Cullen, William B.
  - Hutchinson, Tracy, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Jewish Employment and Vocational Service, 1959,1971 (Box 2)
  - Jimerson, Lidelia (Mrs. A.J.), 1989 (Box 2)
  - John, Terri M., 1984,n.d. (Box 2)
  - Johnson, Frederick (Box 2)
    -See Ser.I, American Anthropological Association
  - Jones, Leroy O., 1951 (Box 2)
  - Kent, Don (Box 2)
    -See Ser.I, Deardorff, Merle H.
  - Kennedy, Robert J., 1983 (Box 2)
    -See also Westvaco
  - Kluckhohn, Clyde, 1954 (Box 2)
  - LeFever, Carole, 1987,n.d. (Box 2)
  - Leshner, Saul S., 1991-1992 (Box 2)
  - Leslie, Charles, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Main Line "School Night" Association, 1953 (Box 2)
  - Neighborhood Centre of Philadelphia, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Nephew, Oscar (Family of), [1987] (Box 2)
  - New York Folklore Society, 1980 (Box 2)
  - New York Public Library, 1953 (Box 2)
  - New York (State). Dept. of Social Welfare, 1953 (Box 2)
  - New York (State). Parks, Recreation and Historic Preservation, 1983 (Box 2)
  - New York State Museum and Science Service, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Oberholtzer, Cath, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Painter, Levinus K., 1953 (Box 2)
  - Pennsylvania. Pennsylvania Historical and Museum Commission, 1953,n.d. (Box 2)
  - Pennsylvania State Employment Service, 1959-1971 (Box 2)
    -See also Ser.I, Selecky, Paul R.
  - Redeye, Clara (Box 2)
    Redeye, Sherman
    - Folder #1, 1946-1960 (Box 2)
    - Folder #2, 1961-1974 (Box 2)
  - Redeye, Sherman, 1947 (Box 2)
    -See also Ser.I, Redeye, Clara
  - Richards, Henry M. M., 1962 (Box 2)
  - Riegelman, Strasser, Schwartz & Spiegelberg, 1950 (Box 2)
  - St. Bonaventure University. Library, 1962 (Box 2)
  - School District of Philadelphia, 1960,1970 (Box 2)
  - Seiler, Joe, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Selecky, Paul R., 1960 (Box 2)
    Pennsylvania State Employment Service
  - Smith, Amy L., 1988 (Box 2)
  - Smithsonian Institution. Bureau of American Ethnology, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Snow, Kenneth (Mrs.), 1946 (Box 2)
  - Snow, Lena, 1947-1952,n.d. (Box 2)
  - Society of Friends. Philadelphia Yearly Meeting. Indian Committee, 1956 (Box 2)
  - Solenberger, Robert, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Speck, Frank G., 1945-1950,n.d. (Box 2)
    General, Alex
    Harris, Helen
  - Speck, Frank G. (Mrs.), 1951-1952 (Box 2)
  - Spoehr, Alexander, 1951 (Box 2)
  - Stone, Mark K., 1991 (Box 2)
  - Supper, Helen, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Swarthmore College. Friends Historical Library, 1953 (Box 2)
  - Tanner, Helen Hornbeck, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Taplinger, Dick (Box 2)
  - Teeters, Negley, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Temple University, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Uhlig, Richard H., 1960 (Box 2)
  - Unidentified, 1969,1987,1991,n.d. (Box 2)
  - United States. Army Engineer District, Pittsburgh (Box 2)
  - United States. Dept. of Commerce. Bureau of the Census, 1952 (Box 2)
  - United States. Dept. of Health, Education, and Welfare. Social Security Administration, 1961,1971 (Box 2)
  - United States. Dept. of Labor, 1960-1964 (Box 2)
  - United States. Dept. of the Interior. Office of Indian Affairs, 1952-1953 (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan, 1959 (Box 2)
  - University of Pennsylvania, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Voget, Fred W. (Box 2)
  - Wallace, Anthony F.C. (Box 2)
  - Wannemacher, Ed H., 1950 (Box 2)
  - Webb, Charles G., 1958 (Box 2)
  - Westvaco, 1983 (Box 2)
    Kennedy, Robert J.
  - Whitacre, M. Elizabeth, 1953 (Box 2)
  - White, Clayton C., 1941-1942,1953 (Box 2)
  - Witthoft, John, 1954 (Box 2)
  - WRCV, 1960 (Box 2)
- Series II. Subject files, 1758-1994, 0.5 boxes; 0.25 linear foot
  Reports, legal documents, and newspaper clippings. The folders are arranged alphabetically by title. The earliest items in this series are transcriptions from the Quaker Collection at Haverford College. Also of note is a printed booklet of sketches of Iroquois life done by Jesse J. Cornplanter in 1903.
  - American Anthropological Association, 1949 (Box 3)
  - Anthropology, Description of the Profession, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Cartoon, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Cayuga Reservation--Map, 1795 (Box 3)
    -See Oversized
  - Clippings, 1948-1984,n.d. (Box 3)
  - Concentrated Employment Program, 1963-1971 (Box 3)
  - Conference on Iroquois Research (3rd), 1947 (Box 3)
  - Cornplanter, Jesse J., 1903 (Box 3)
  - "Deed from the Six Nations to William Trent and Others"--Transcript Copy, 1769 (Box 3)
  - Haverford College Library. The Quaker Collection, 1758,1795-1815 (Box 3)
    transcript copies
  - Illinois--Map, n.d. (Box 3)
    Native American Image note: Map of Illinois showing areas of Native American settlements, such as, Ottowa, Potawatami, Sac and Fox, Kickapoo, Iowa. See Oversize.
  - Iowa--Maps, 1795,1816,1825,n.d. (Box 3)
    Native American Images note: Six maps of Iowa with color key codes showing areas of Sioux, Sac and Fox settlements. Two charts of forty Native American sites from 1700-1837. -See Oversized
  - Iowa State Historical Society, [1951] (Box 3)
    2 Folders
  - Jimerson, Avery J., Sr., [1974],1986 (Box 3)
  - Kansas--Map, n.d. (Box 3)
    Native American Images note: Negative print of map of Kansas and Nebraska. -See Oversized
  - Keating, John. Index to His Letter Book--Transcript Copy, 1819-1821 (Box 3)
  - Kinzua Dam, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Labor Terms, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Minnesota--Map, n.d. (Box 3)
    Native American images note: Map shows Native American settlements within the state. -See Oversized
  - Missouri--Maps, n.d. (Box 3)
    Native American images note: Three maps showing waterways and Native American treaty boundaries. -See Oversized
  - Oneida Nation of New York vs. The State of New York, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Pennsylvania State Employment Service, 1961,n.d. (Box 3)
  - Philadelphia Anthropological Society, 1948,1950 (Box 3)
  - Saint Joseph's Indian School, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Six Nations Population, 1789-1790 (Box 3)
  - Wampum, 1885-1950,n.d. (Box 3)
  - Wisconsin--Map, n.d. (Box 3)
    Native American images note: black ink map by Snyderman with Sac and Fox settlements. -See Oversized
  - Wounded Knee School, [1994] (Box 3)
- Series III. Works by Snyderman, 1939-ca.1985, 1.5 boxes; 0.75 linear foot
  Snyderman's typewritten drafts and research notes for articles and reviews. There are several reports that Snyderman wrote as historical background material for lawyer Felix S. Cohen. There are also unpublished and published manuscripts on such topics as Seneca folklore, Seneca medicine, and ethnohistory. Snyderman's reports for the Pennsylvania Bureau of Employment Security appear in this series as well.
  - Allegany Reservation--Notes, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Blacksnake--Notes, [194-] (Box 3)
  - "Bohemia: the Underworld of Art"--Ms., [1939] (Box 3)
  - Coppermine Journey by Farley Mowat--Review, 1958 (Box 3)
  - Cornplanter--Notes, n.d. (Box 3)
  - "The Economic Life of the Ohio Indians"--Ms. (Box 3)
    Native American images note: Two crayon colored maps. -See also Oversized
  - Encyclopedia Americana Entries, [1955?] (Box 3)
  - "Ethno History: Amalgam of Anthropology and History"--Ms., [1953] (Box 3)
  - "An Ethnological Discussion of Allegany Seneca Wampum Folklore"--Ms., [198-] (Box 3)
  - "Experimental Program for Hard-to-Place Youth"--Ms., [1960] (Box 3)
  - Field Notes (Box 4)
    - Folder #1, 1946 (Box 4)
    - Folder #2, 1950-1951 (Box 4)
  - Halliday Jackson's Journal of a Visit Paid to the Indians of New York (1806)--Review, 1959 (Box 4)
  - "The Historical Method and Its Use in Anthropology"--Ms., [1950?] (Box 4)
  - "Illinois"--Ms., n.d. (Box 4)
  - "Introduction to the Study of Iroquois Government"--Ms., [1948] (Box 4)
    "Prepared for Speck" appeared on orig. folder
  - Medicine (Seneca)--Notes, 1950, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Messianic Movements--Notes, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Midwinter Rites of the Cayuga Longhouse by Frank G. Speck--Review, [1949] (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous--Notes and Research, 1946-1965, n.d. (Box 4)
  - "Notes on a Visit to the Seneca Nation of Indians by John Pierce and Joshua Sharples"--Notes (Box 4)
  - "Notes on Oneida of Wisconsin"--Ms., [1950] (Box 4)
  - "Notes on the Population of Selected Tribes West of the Ohio"--Ms., n.d. (Box 4)
  - "O He Yoh: the Once Beautiful Country and Home of Indian Peoples"--Ms., [1971] (Box 4)
  - "Ohio"--Ms., n.d. (Box 4)
  - Parrish, John--Notes, n.d. (Box 4)
  - "The Philadelphia Pilot Placement and Counseling Project"--Ms., 5 May 1958 (Box 4)
  - "References", n.d. (Box 4)
  - Reports for Felix Cohen--Research, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Seneca Witchcraft--Notes, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Simmons, Henry, Jr.--Notes, n.d. (Box 4)
  - "Suggested Guide for Training New Interviewers"--Ms., n.d. (Box 4)
  - "Witches, Witchcraft, and Allegany Seneca Medicine"--Ms. (Box 4)
- Series IV. Works by others, 1758-1984, 1 box; 0. 5 linear foot
  Articles, notes, and papers written by colleagues and students of Snyderman, as well as transcriptions of works from the late 1700s and early 1800s. This series is arranged alphabetically by author and then by title. There are works by William N. Fenton and several files of notes by Merle H. Deardorff. Also included in this series are folk tales recorded by Clara Redeye and Helen Harris.
  - "Flag Day in Washington", Alexander, Heap (Box 5)
    Ms.
  - "On the Paganism of the Civilized Iroquois of Ontario", Boyle, David (Box 5)
  - Notes, Brodie, Paul (Box 5)
    Transcript Copy
  - Cold Spring, Deardorff, Merle H., d.1971 (Box 5)
    Notes
  - Miscellaneous, Deardorff, Merle H., d.1971 (Box 5)
  - Henry Simmons, Jr., Deardorff, Merle H., d.1971 (Box 5)
  - Deardorff, Merle H., d.1971 (Box 5)
    Transcriptions
  - "Observations on Research and Practice in the Transitional Sheltered Workshop", Depp, Frederick C. (Box 5)
  - "Coldspring Notes", 11 Aug. 1946; Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005 (Box 5)
  - "Condolence Council. Six Nations Reserve", 31 March 1951; Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005 (Box 5)
  - "Condolence Council. Six Nations Reserve", 14 May 1948; Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005 (Box 5)
    Address
  - "A Day on the Allegheny Ox-Bow", Jul. 1945; Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005 (Box 5)
  - Diplomacy and Indian Gifts: Anglo-French Rivalry Along the Ohio and North-West Frontiers, 1748-1763. By Wilbur R. Jacobs, [1950]; Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005 (Box 5)
    Review
  - "Iroquois Studies at the Mid-Century", [1951]; Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005 (Box 5)
    Ms
  - "Locality as a Basic Factor in the Development of Iroquois Social Structure"--, 1949; Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous, 1933, 1942, n.d.; Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005 (Box 5)
  - "The Modern Shtetl: A Study of Cultural Persistance"--, 1962; Freilich, Morris (Box 5)
    MS
  - "Early African Culture as an Indication of Present Negro Potentialities", Frobenius, Leo (Box 5)
  - "Transcription of the Original Records of the Western Missionary Society"--, 15 Apr. 1936; George, Edward I. (Box 5)
  - "Anthropological Research, Action and Education in Modern Nations: With Special Reference to the U.S.A.", Oct. 1968; Goldstein, Marcus Solomon (Box 5)
  - "Frank Gouldsmith Speck (1881-1950)", n.d.; Hallowell, A. Irving, (Alfred Irving), 1892-1974 (Box 5)
  - Folk talkes, 1948, 1984; Harris, Helen (Box 5)
  - Folk talkes, [1984]; Harris, Linda (Box 5)
  - Journal, 1806; Philips, John (Box 5)
    Cy
  - "Notes on a Visit to the Seneca Nation of Indians", 1798; Pierce, John and Joshua Sharples (Box 5)
    Transcript Cy
  - Oneida Journal, 1798; Pierce, John (Box 5)
  - Journal of Journey from Philadelphia to Wyoming--Transcript Copy, 1758; Post, Frederick (Box 5)
  - Folk Tales, 1947-1976, n.d.; Redeye, Clara (Box 5)
  - "Research on the Sac and Fox Tribe of Oklahoma", 11 Aug. 1949; Rochnes, Louis L. (Box 5)
  - "Delaware Indian Designs"--, 1933; Tantaquidgeon, Gladys (Box 5)
  - "Anthropology and the Social Worker", [198-]; Unidentified (Box 5)
  - "Preliminary Report of the Seneca-Cayuga Tribe of Oklahoma", n.d.; Unidentified (Box 5)
  - "Preliminary Report on Land Rights of the Wisconsin Oneida Tribe"--, Unidentified (Box 5)
  - "Shawnees", n.d.; Unidentified (Box 5)
  - "The New Religion of the Iroquois"--, n.d.; Witthoft, John (Box 5)
  - "Council at Six Nations"--, 4 Oct. 1848; Wright, Asher (Box 5)
- Series V. Photographs, 1790-1993, 1 box; 0.5 linear foot